Our planet may be home
我们的星球
to 30 million different kinds of animals and plants.
大约是3千多万种动植物的家
Each individual locked in its own life-long fight for survival.
每个物种都会为生存而奋斗一生
Everywhere you look, on land or in the ocean, there are extraordinary
无论你将目光投向何方，陆地还是海洋
examples of the lengths living things go to to stay alive.
总会看到为生存而战的壮观事例
This is the coast of Florida.
这里是弗罗里达海岸
Here, strange scars on the sea bed
海床上奇怪的图案
hint at one animal's remarkable strategy.
暗示着某种动物独特的战术
These are bottlenose dolphins,
它们是宽吻海豚
one of the most intelligent animals on Earth.
地球上最聪明的动物之一
Their prey is very elusive, fast-swimming fish.
它们的猎物是迅速、灵巧的鱼
But the dolphins have invented a completely new way of hunting.
但是海豚们进化出了一种全新的捕猎技巧
By beating its tail down hard, this dolphin stirs up the shallow silt.
通过用力向下拍尾巴，将淤泥搅动起来
And by swimming in a tight circle
再通过绕圈游动
it creates a ring of mushrooming mud around a shoal of fish.
用浑浊的泥水将一大群鱼包围起来
The contracting ring traps the fish just like a net.
再像收网一样缩小包围圈
Panicked, the fish jump to escape.
由于恐慌，小鱼们四下乱跳
Right into the open mouths of the waiting dolphins.
海豚们张嘴以待，很多鱼落入口中
Again and again, the lead dolphin creates a circle,
通过默契的组织、协作
before they all line up with perfect timing.
海豚们造出一个接一个的包围圈
These dolphins are the only ones known to have developed this hunting behaviour and it gives them an edge.
这群海豚,用这种目前已知的独一无二的捕猎方式奠定一种优势
This sort of advantage may mean the difference between life and death
这种优势在这个适者生存的世界里
in the survival of the fittest.
也许就决定着生或死
This series reveals the most spectacular and extraordinary
这些事例能显示出动植物
strategies that animals and plants have developed to stay alive.
一些奇特而又壮观的生存策略
For every creature, every day is full of challenges,
对任何物种来说,每一天都充满挑战
all of which must be overcome, somehow, in order to survive.
必须克服，然后生存下来
Kenya, famous for its big cats.
肯尼亚, 以大型猫科动物闻名于世
The supreme hunters.
顶级猎手
Cheetahs specialise in hunting at speed.
猎豹专靠速度捕猎
Though fast, they are fragile creatures,
尽管很快,但因为自身力量不足
built to sprint after small prey.
它们天生只能捕捉小型猎物
They don't have the strength or weight of a lion
它们不具备像狮子那样的力量和体重
to bring down larger animals.
来扑倒大型猎物
This male is different.
这只公豹是不同的
He doesn't hunt alone. He's learnt that there is strength in numbers.
并不单独捕猎，它明白“豹多力量大”的道理
But here there are not just two, but three cheetahs.
而且不只两头，而是三头
A band of brothers.
兄弟连
They have changed their tactics and, by doing so,
它们改变战术
have taken their prey by surprise.
对猎物发动偷袭
They have learnt that working together
它们学会了只要团结合作
they can bring down large prey.
就能捕捉大的猎物
An ostrich.
鸵鸟
A bird that towers over a cheetah and is more than twice as heavy.
一种远比猎豹高大而且几乎比它们重两倍的鸟
It can't fly to escape danger, but it can lash out with a deadly kick.
虽然逃跑时不能飞，但拥有致命的“弹腿一踢”
A female, unaware as yet, of any danger.
一只雌鸵鸟没有留意到任何危险
Even with three of them this is still highly risky.
即便三头豹子，也要冒较高的风险
If one gets injured the other two couldn't hope to tackle such large prey.
如果有一头受伤，另两头是搞不定这么大的猎物的
On the other hand, if they get it right, the rewards
反之，如果这笔买卖成了
are huge.
回报是相当丰厚的
The male has spotted one of the brothers, but only one.
雄鸵鸟已经发现了一头豹子，只是一头
It's not too worried.
它并没有怎么担心
Then suddenly there are three!
忽然变成三头！
The female is slower to realise the danger
雌鸵鸟意识到危险时，已经有点晚了
and the cheetahs switch targets.
猎豹也改变了目标
It takes the combined effort and weight of all three brothers to bring down this powerful bird.
必须将三头豹子的力量全部联合起来才能制服这种大鸟
Even now the ostrich could land a fatal kick.
即便此时，鸵鸟也会发出最后一击
So far, the brothers are winning.
现在，豹子们赢了
Ostriches have yet to find a way to foil such tactics.
鸵鸟们则必须学会应付这种攻击策略
Other animals have also evolved surprising tactics to outmanoeuvre
其它动物也进化出了类似的集体战术
the enemy, not with brute strength but with extraordinary weapons.
它们的对手，不但有惊人的力量，还有特殊的武器
Madagascar.
马达加斯加
A strange world where nothing is quite as it seems.
一个捉摸不透的奇怪地方
To hunt here requires stealth and subterfuge.
在这里捕猎需要诡秘和花招
And living within the trees is a master of ambush.
在这些树林里生存的一定是伪装大师
A preying mantis.
螳螂
Well camouflaged and lightning quick,
良好的伪装、轻巧的身手
these insects are highly efficient predators.
这种昆虫是高效的猎手
But even they are outgunned.
但即便它全副武装
A chameleon.
变色龙
Its camouflage is exceptional because it can change its skin colour to match its surroundings.
它的伪装极其出色，因为它能够改变皮肤颜色与环境一致
Its eyes move independently to spot prey.
它的两眼能独立转动，侦测猎物
It creeps towards to its victim, until just in range.
悄悄地向目标爬行，直到进入攻击范围
Then it unleashes a super weapon.
然后使出超级武器
Its tongue shoots out at 15 metres per second.
它的舌头能以15米/秒的速度弹射而出
And not only hits, but grasps its target.
击中目标同时能将其牢牢黏住
But few hunters are always successful.
不过很少的猎手能做到百战百胜
For them a hunt is just one meal.
它们捕猎只为果腹
For prey, the stakes are higher.
但对被捕者而言就惨了
It's life...or death.
非生即死
As Antarctica moves from spring into summer, the inlets and bays, once choked with ice, become free.
南极洲由春入夏时，那些一度冰封的海湾得以解冻
And animals move in to feed.
动物们开始觅食
These are crabeater seals.
南极食蟹海豹
They don't actually eat crabs, but krill, small shrimps that swarm in their billions in these waters.
它们并非真的吃螃蟹，而是捕食这片水域里以数十亿集群的小虾
Resting on a large ice floe, these crabeaters are safe.
这些海豹躺在大的浮冰上是比较安全的
But as soon as they enter the water, they are on their guard,
一旦下水，就得十分警惕
for good reason.
事出有因
Killer whales.
虎鲸（逆戟鲸）
Here in Antarctica, many killer whales prey only on fish.
在南极许多虎鲸只吃鱼
But these whales are different, they specialise in hunting seals.
但这一群不同，它们专猎食海豹
This seal swimming to open water is unaware of the danger heading his way.
这只海豹下水后，没意识到危险正迎头袭来
Until now.
直到现在
He's in real trouble. There is no escape unless he can hide behind this small piece of floating ice.
这次真的麻烦了，无法逃脱 除非躲在这块小浮冰后面
But he's been spotted and surrounded.
但它已经被发现，并被包围
Now agility is his only chance.
就看够不够敏捷了
He dodges for his life, staying as close as he can to the iceberg.
拼命地闪躲，不肯离开冰块半步
He's tiring.
它已累坏了
And the whales tighten the circle, going for the kill.
虎鲸们缩小包围圈，准备吃掉它
But hunters don't always get their own way.
但捕食者们并不是每次都能如愿
In the end, the seal's determination and skill, using
最后，海豹的决心和技巧
the ice for protection, kept him just out of reach.
利用冰块作掩护，保住了性命
And the whales move on.
虎鲸们则继续远征
Recently it's been observed that killer whales
最近的观察得知
are much more successful when hunting other types of seal.
虎鲸们在捕食其它种类的海豹时成功率更高
Crabeaters like this put up too much of a fight.
像这只食蟹海豹，备战太充分了
For creatures living in the open ocean there is nowhere to hide from predators.
生活在开放水域的生物则没地方躲避
But there is safety in numbers.
群体生活则相对安全
One fish, however, has evolved a different escape tactic.
有一种鱼进化出了独特的逃跑方法
To leave the water completely, take to the air and fly!
完全离开水面, 空中飞翔！
After a huge effort to get airborne, flying fish
经过一番努力的空中飞行
can glide 200 metres or so, to escape the predators chasing them.
飞鱼可以滑翔200米，来逃脱捕食者的追逐
Not all animals are hunters, many are vegetarians.
并非所有生物都是猎手，有些食素
But the battle between animals and plants can also be intense.
但即便是动植物之间，关系也会相当紧张
Boa Vista, central Brazil.
Boa Vista, 巴西中部
This valley is peppered with strangely pitted rocks.
这个山谷布满了奇形怪状的石头
These are not natural formations but the legacy of a long struggle between one animal and one plant.
这些并非自然形成的，而是动植物长期斗争的产物
Brown-tufted capuchins, highly intelligent monkeys.
棕毛僧猴, 极度聪明的猴子
They spend their nights in the safety of caves,
晚上它们在安全的洞里过夜
emerging each morning to find food.
早晨则出来觅食
Down in the valley is a particular favourite.
特别喜欢下到山谷里
A nut palm.
椰果
The palms produce huge seeds, but they have very strong shells
果实里种子很大很多, 但是有坚硬的外壳
that protect them against attack from hungry animals.
防止饥饿的动物们取食
For the capuchins this is a war of attrition.
对猴子来说这是一场消耗战
They check which seed is the ripest, and the battle commences.
它们挑出成熟的果子, 开始战斗
The first job is to tear the tough fibrous husk from the nut.
第一步是撕开果子表面的粗纤维
He doesn't try to crack the nut straight away,
它并不是直接将果实掰开
but drops it to the ground.
而是将它放在地上
He's learnt that a nut should be given a week or so drying in the sun.
它知道一周后果实就会被太阳晒干
These are ones he prepared earlier.
这些是它先前准备好的
He taps them to see if they're ready.
敲打，看是否已经好了
This huge flat rock is his anvil.
这个大石块就是它的工具
And this is a hammer.
锤子
It's made of a different and much harder rock than the anvil.
这种石头比锤子还要坚硬
Now something extraordinary happens.
奇迹就要发生了
The capuchins' use of these stone tools requires an exceptional level
棕毛僧猴利用石块
of intelligence, planning and dexterity.
需要极高的技巧、智商和计划
The nut finally cracks and exposes a rich, oily kernel.
果壳最终破裂，露出含油丰富的种子
Youngsters watch and imitate the adults, just as human toddlers do.
小猴子观察并模仿, 就像我们的小孩一样
If they are to become independent,
如果它们想要自立
they must learn to crack their own nuts.
就得学会如何打开这些硬果
But the learning process is long, with many frustrations.
但是学习的过程相当漫长，充满沮丧
They learn early on that to do a job properly,
它们很早就知道想要成功
you need the right tool.
就得有合适的工具
It can take eight years for a capuchin to master this art
一般要花上八年时间才能练成这精湛的技艺
and overcome the palm's formidable defences.
攻破椰果坚不可摧的防线
But some plants have turned the tables and feed on animals.
但有些植物反败为胜，专吃动物
This is a highly sophisticated trap. The bait,
这是一个极度精巧的陷阱
sugary nectar around the rim of the disc.
盘子的周围布满了香甜的蜜汁
The triggers, fine hairs, two of which have to be touched within 20 seconds of each other.
一旦碰到了这些小刺中的两根，就发动了机关
The victim, a fly which finds the colour and nectar irresistible.
一只苍蝇受不了这颜色和香味儿的诱惑
One.
一根
Two.
两根
When triggered, the trap snaps shut so fast that the fly is imprisoned.
一旦触发，笼子迅速合拢，苍蝇无法逃脱
The Venus flytrap now slowly digests its victim.
维纳斯捕蝇草现在慢慢地消化食物
Life's challenges are more than just finding food.
生存的挑战不仅仅在于觅食
In every animal's life there comes a time when its mind turns to breeding.
每种动物都会有繁育期
One creature's approach is mind-boggling.
有种生物的表现令人惊异
Malaysia.
马来群岛
This strange insect has been lying dormant on the forest floor.
这种奇怪的昆虫一直蛰伏在森林的地表
Once safe in the trees, these males hide among the leaves and begin an extraordinary transformation.
一旦树上安全了，这些雄虫就躲进树叶中，开始奇特的变形
One that will make the difference between fathering offspring or not.
有个特征显示出祖先和后代的差别
He begins by gulping in air bubbles, forcing them up into his head.
它开始大口地空气进入头部
He then pumps the bubbles into the stalks supporting his eyes,
然后把气泡挤到“眼棒”里去
just like blowing up a balloon.
就像吹气球一样
And this is what earns these creatures their name,
这也使它得到了这个名字：
the stalk-eyed fly.
棒眼蝇
A few final adjustments to straighten out any remaining creases
最后只需将褶皱稍稍抹平
and he's ready for action.
它已经准备好了
They may look unwieldy, but eyes on stalks improve not only his ability
看起来好像有些笨重，但这种“棒眼”不但可以更有利于发现天敌
to spot predators, but they are key when it comes to winning females.
也是赢得异性青睐的关键
In the evening both males and females gather and the males begin to size one another up, eyeball to eyeball.
夜间雌雄聚集，雄虫们开始逐对逐对比较眼睛的尺寸
Having the widest eye span puts you at the top of the pecking order.
眼距最宽的得到最高的优先权
The eye stalks are not weapons, they're measuring sticks,
棒眼不是武器，而是标尺
used to gauge how big, and so how strong, a male is.
衡量雄虫的强壮程度
But there's trouble if two top males have exactly the same eye width.
如果两只头号雄虫拥有同样的眼宽
Then the contest descends into a brawl.
打架就不可避免
Defeated.
失败
The winner. He now has the right to mate with all the females nearby.
胜者，将有权和附近所有的雌性交配
The rather gentlemanly way stalk-eyed flies settle their differences over females is not the only way.
像棒眼蝇这样绅士的举动并非争夺雌性的唯一方式
Some animals are much more violent.
许多动物更为暴力
It's the dry season in Zambia.
赞比亚的旱季
The lagoons are either baked dry, or the mud is so thick animals get stuck, with fatal consequences.
河湾要么被烤干，要么过于泥泞而给动物们带来致命的危险
This male hippo has been living in one small lagoon, but as it dries, it's turning into a death trap.
这只公河马一直生活在此。到了旱季，这里便成了死亡地带
Understandably, the females that once shared it with him have all left.
不难理解，曾经与它同居的母河马们都离开了
Even if he wants to, he can't stay much longer.
就算它想呆，也呆不长
He needs water to keep cool and females to mate with.
它需要水来降温，更需要母河马
And this is where they all are.
它们都在这儿呢
Almost all the hippos in the area are in what is left of the Luangwa River,
这个区域几乎所有的河马都到了Luangwa River的这里
because it's the last place where there's still deep water.
这里是唯一水还较深的地方
This bend is controlled by an all-powerful male.
这个河湾被一头强大的公河马占据
Since the drought many more females have joined his herd.
自干旱以来许多母河马纷纷投奔而来
They are happy to live cheek by jowl, but any male who comes here
它们一起其乐融融，但公河马也来了
in the hope of mating must first defeat the overlord.
想要得到母河马，必须打败这里的霸主
The wandering male arrives and has a decision to make - submit or fight.
外来者必须做出决定：战斗或屈服
Victory for the overlord.
霸主获胜了
His domination of his channel in the river remains and with it mating rights with the females.
它仍享有这个水域的控制权，以及与母河马的交配权
The loser is alive, but is an outcast.
失败者虽然活着，但已经被遗弃
He retreats to another part of the river where it's so shallow that no females will follow.
它撤到河的另一处，但那里太浅，没有母河马会跟随
His chance to father offspring is over for now.
它传宗接代的愿望就此落空
For some animals the challenges of breeding are not about fighting but about courtship.
对一些动物而言，繁育的挑战不在于争斗，而在于求爱技巧
Among birds, displays, songs and rituals can reach extraordinary levels of complexity and beauty.
对鸟类而言，物品展示、歌唱和舞蹈会达到极高的水平，复杂而优美
During spring, on the freshwater lakes of Oregon,
春季，俄勒冈州的淡水湖
grebes join together to renew their partnership.
Gf们聚集在一起，重新找感情
The ceremony starts with a series of graceful duets,
仪式以一种优美的二重唱开始
in which one partner echoes the actions of the other.
夫唱妻和
But the real test comes now.
但真正的测试来了
Only the strongest and the most faithful
只有最强健和守信的
are prepared to join together for the final exultant dance.
才能一起跳最后的舞蹈
Those animals which have young now face a whole new set of challenges,
这些有了后代的动物又面临全新的挑战
to protect and nurture their offspring.
保护和养育它们
In the cold waters of the northern Pacific Ocean, there lives a giant.
在北太平洋的冷水海域，生活着一种巨兽
A giant Pacific octopus at over four metres long.
一种巨型章鱼，体长大四米
She is hunting, not for prey, but for a den.
她在寻找，不为食物，而是巢穴
Somewhere to settle down and hide.
一个隐蔽可安顿的地方
Her den has to be just right.
必须大小合适
She's going to live here for the rest of her life.
她打算在此度过余生
She's carrying fertilised eggs,
她携带着受精过的卵
and now, happy and settled, she lays them.
现在，她可以产卵了
100,000 of them.
大概10万只
Over the next six months she carefully tends her precious brood.
接下来六个月，她会细心呵护自己的亲骨肉
She caresses them with her arms
用她的触手爱抚它们
to keep them free of algae and properly supplied with oxygen.
弄掉黏附的水藻，保证充足的供氧
This is her first and only brood.
这是她第一也是唯一的后代
And so she takes great care of them.
所以付出再多也不辞
While she's guarding her eggs she doesn't leave the den.
照料过程中她不会离开巢穴
Not once.
从不
Unable to feed,
不能进食
she is starving.
她在挨饿
Her last act of devotion is to blow water over the eggs to help them hatch.
她最后一丝力气，也是鼓动水流，帮助卵孵化
Young, fully-developed octopus pop out.
幼小的、发育完全的章鱼破卵而出
Though only a few will survive to adulthood, she's given them the best chance she can.
尽管只有少数能活到成年，但它们的妈妈给了它们最好的开始
After her long and lonely vigil,
经过漫长而又孤独的守候
she is dead.
她死掉了
Surely this sacrifice must make her one of nature's most devoted mothers.
无疑，这种牺牲精神，使得她成为自然界最有爱心的妈妈之一
Here, 30 metres beneath the Costa Rican forest canopy, another dedicated mother
在哥斯达尼加森林之下，有另一个专注的母亲
ensures that her young also have the best possible start in life.
确保她的后代有个最好的起步
This tiny strawberry poison arrow frog, only the size of a finger nail, is guarding her fertilised eggs.
这种小型的草莓色箭毒蛙，只有指甲般大小，正在守候产下的卵
Whilst the eggs and tadpoles are developing, she and her mate keep
从卵发育到蝌蚪，她和伴侣
watch, making sure that they are safe from predators.
一直守候，确保它们不会被天敌吃掉
But they can't stay here for ever.
但它们不可能一直守候
The leaf litter is drying out and tadpoles need water.
树叶快干掉了，蝌蚪需要水
She must do something, and fast.
她必须尽快处理
She needs to move them and so encourages one tadpole to climb on her back.
必须转移它们。于是她鼓励一只蝌蚪爬到她背上
She now begins an epic journey.
开始了史诗般的旅程
But it's not to a pond, as you might expect,
出乎你意料的是，她并不去水塘
she is looking for something very particular.
她有特殊的目标
Her journey takes her across the forest floor to the foot of a tall tree and then she starts to climb.
她穿过空地，来到一棵大树的脚下，然后开始攀爬
For such a little frog it is a marathon ascent,
对一只蛙来说，这是一次马拉松式的攀爬
like a human mother climbing the Empire State Building with a child on her back.
如同一位人类母亲驼着孩子爬上帝国大厦
She's looking for a plant, a bromeliad, growing on the tree.
她在找一种长在树上的凤梨科植物
It holds a pool of water at its centre, the perfect nursery pool for a developing tadpole.
它的中央有个盛水的小池子，完美的蝌蚪育儿所
In slides her youngster.
她放下孩子
But this is only one of six tadpoles.
但这只是六个中的一个
She must rush back down to rescue the others.
她必须冲回去营救剩下的孩子
One by one she collects them and carries each to its own bromeliad.
将它们一只一只地背到各自的小池子里
But there is another problem.
但还有个问题
The little pools contain no food.
小池中没有食物
So she has to provide it.
她必须提供
She lays an unfertilised egg in each pool for her tadpoles to eat.
向每个小池里排一颗未受精的卵作为小蝌蚪的食物
And then she leaves.
然后离开
But one egg won't sustain a growing tadpole for long,
但一颗卵不足以维持小蝌蚪多长时间
so she has to return every few days with another egg.
所以她必须隔几天就回来排卵
Over the next two weeks she can climb almost half a mile tending her young.
接下来的两周，她几乎要爬行半英里来照看后代
An astonishing feat for such a tiny creature.
这种小动物所创造的惊人奇迹
While she's busy delivering eggs,
就在她忙于产卵时
the tadpole grows legs and its tail begins to disappear.
小蝌蚪长出了腿，尾巴消失了
And then one day it leaves its bromeliad nursery for ever
直到一天，永久地离开这个育儿所
and climbs out into the forest.
爬向森林深处
Whilst its mother has a well-deserved rest.
蛙妈妈也可以好好休息一下了
Birds are also diligent parents.
鸟类也是勤劳的父母
Over their lifetime they invest huge effort in just a few young.
它们毕生花费大量心血，照料为数不多的后代
But there is only so much a parent can do.
但只有极少的鸟能做到这样
All along the Antarctic peninsula both male and female chinstrap penguins have been commuting
整个南极的颔带企鹅，雌鸟和雄鸟每天交替
daily from the open ocean to collect food for their chicks.
去海洋里为后代搜集食物
Mouthfuls of krill, caught many miles away at sea, are regurgitated.
从远处带回满嘴的磷虾，然后反刍给幼鸟
But one day the chicks wait in vain for food.
但有一天幼鸟们没等到食物
Their parents do not return.
父母不见归来
The chicks now face life on their own.
幼鸟们现在必须独自面对
This is the toughest time in an animal's life
这是动物一生中最难熬的时刻
and some are not going to make it.
有些没有撑过去
Over the next few days, driven by hunger, the chicks make their way down to the shore.
接下来的几天，在饥饿的驱使下，幼鸟们自己来到海边
Instinct tells them they have to head out to sea.
本能告诉它们，必须下海
Built to withstand the cold, they have already accumulated
它们体内已经储存了一些用于御寒的脂肪
a layer of fat, and their outer feathers act as a waterproof shield.
外层的羽毛像一层防水衣
But they still have to learn to swim.
但它们必须要学会游泳
The polar sea is challenging enough
南极的海洋充满挑战
but with a change in the wind,
风的一点改变
a slick of broken ice has choked the bay.
一块破冰阻塞了海湾
For any penguin this ice presents a real problem.
这块冰对任何企鹅来说都是麻烦
But for the chicks it's a disaster.
对小企鹅来说就是灾难
They must get through this barrier to the open water, if they are to feed.
如果想吃到食物，就必须越过障碍到达空阔的水域
One, perhaps hungrier or braver than the rest,
有一只，也许是受不了饥饿，也许是更为勇敢
leads the way and tries skittering over the top, while the others watch.
在众鸟关注下带头试着从顶部划过去
The ice is hard to swim through, and progress is painfully slow.
冰面很难游过，过程缓慢而痛苦
A leopard seal.
海豹
This chick never had the chance to learn how to avoid the seal.
这只幼鸟从没学过如何避开海豹
Its end is inevitable.
结局不言而喻
The leopard seal efficiently flays the chick, tearing off a small piece with each throw.
海豹熟练地将幼鸟扔出，每一次都撕下一块肉
Others take their chance.
余下的幼鸟也要冒险
But the leopard seal is now ready for its next victim.
现在海豹准备捕获下一个目标
It's a lottery, and the lucky chicks make it out to open water.
只有最幸运的幼鸟能够到达开阔水域
There is still an element of chance in life which an individual can do little about.
生活中总是有那么一点点被上天注定的机遇
In the end, overcoming life's challenges,
最终，战胜困难
whether finding enough to eat or outwitting your predators,
找到足够的食物或者战胜天敌
is only significant if life's final challenge can be met.
是生命遇到挑战的唯一意义
From a tiny frog dedicating weeks to her few cherished tadpoles, to an orang-utan who spends
从花费数周照顾蝌蚪的小箭毒蛙
eight years bringing up her baby,
到花费8年时间养育后代的大猩猩
individual animals strive to reach this one ultimate goal,
每个动物都为同一个目标奋斗
to pass on their genes and to ensure the survival of the next generation.
将自己的基因传递下去，并保证后代的生存
Ultimately, in nature,
最终，在自然界
that is what life is all about.
这就是生命的意义
During the three years it took to film Life, our camera crews
在拍摄《生命》的三年间 我们摄制组
visited every continent on Earth, but the most challenging was Antarctica.
探访了地球五大洲 但最刺激的还是南极洲
Here filming was only possible
在这里拍摄唯一可能
with the help of an extraordinary range of people and organisations.
得到的帮助来自一批特殊的人和组织
An Air Force jet delivering supplies to McMurdo research station
空军将供给运送到麦克默多研究站
ferried one of our crews to the Ross Ice Shelf.
将我们的一组人员空运到罗斯冰架
And on the other side of the continent a team sailed for five days
在大陆的另一面 一队人马航行了五天
across the Drake Passage to reach the Antarctic peninsular.
跨越德雷克海峡抵达了南极半岛
Once there, a small crew was put ashore on Deception Island
一小队人曾经登陆奇幻岛
to spend a month camping on the edge of a penguin colony.
露宿了一个月 与群居的企鹅为伴
Two people and 200,000 penguins.
两个人与20万只企鹅
Another team joined scientists drilling through the ice
另一组人加入了钻冰的科学家行列
to explore the beautiful and bizarre world below.
探索下面美丽多姿的世界
But the hardiest and most ambitious shoot involved four film crews,
然而最顽强最具野心的拍摄涉及了四个摄制组
a celebrated French yachtsman and the Ministry of Defence.
一名著名的法国帆船运动员以及国防部
The teams had a two-month window
摄制组有两个月的最佳时间
to film Antarctica's two top predators in action.
来拍摄南极洲两种顶级食肉动物的活动
We knew that one could be found prowling the coast of
我们知道 可以发现一种徘徊在奇幻岛岸边
Rosenthal Island, waiting for young penguins to take their first plunge.
等待着年幼的企鹅首次入水
And the man to take us there was Jerome Poncet.
带领我们的是杰罗姆.庞塞特
He skippered the first yacht to sail south of the Antarctic Circle and has been back every year for the past 35.
他是首次扬帆南极圈以南的快艇的船长 ，过去35年里每年都要回去一次
He knows Antarctic sailing like no-one else.
他对南极航行的了解 无人可与比肩
His yacht, the Golden Fleece, is not an ice breaker,
他的快艇 金羊毛号 不是破冰船
but Jerome has his own unique way of getting through.
然而杰罗姆却又其独特的穿越方式
He shunts one floe against another
他调动一块浮冰来撞击另一块浮冰
to clear a way through like playing marbles.
来清除通道 犹如玩弹珠游戏一般
Jerome, once he gets his teeth into,
杰罗姆 一旦神情严肃起来
into a situation he doesn't like to let it go.
就不会继续前行了
So, maybe we'll be here for a few hours yet.
所以我们就会在这里呆上几个小时
Jerome is determined to get through this channel.
杰罗姆坚决要穿越这条通道
We talk about hundred, hundreds of tonnes,
我们要对付的有数百吨
maybe 1,000, 250,000 tonnes or more.
或许上千 数万吨
It's a pooling of water, you have to push.
这一汪水 你必须将它推开
Some marbles are just too big.
有些冰块是在是大
For now, Jerome is foiled and has to moor for the night.
眼下杰罗姆遭受了挫折，不得不停泊过夜
For him, tying up to 100,000 tonnes of ice
对他来说，停泊在10万吨冰里
is just another day at the office.
只是很平常的事情
Progress is slow, but they need to get to Rosenthal before the penguins leave.
前行缓慢，但是他们必须在企鹅离开前抵达罗森塔尔
They make it through and the penguins are still there.
他们要通过 而企鹅依然还在
Chinstrap penguin chicks fledge at a particular time of year.
颊带企鹅幼崽在每年特定的时段里羽毛丰满
The crew knew this would draw leopard seals like a magnet.
摄制组知道这就像磁铁一般吸引着豹斑海豹
Leopard seals are giants among their kind, they have teeth
豹斑海豹是海豹中的巨人，它们的牙齿尺寸超过狮子
bigger than a lion and a mouth that can open nearly 180 degrees.
而且嘴能够打开接近180度
How close can Doug get?
道格可以靠得多近呢？
With this seal, very.
与这只海豹 亲密接触
He loses interest in his reflection
它对自己的镜像失去了兴趣
and goes back to eating penguins.
回头吃企鹅去了
That was very exciting.
太令人兴奋了
He was a super seal,
它是一只了不起的海豹
super seal, gave me lots of action nice and close,
了不起的海豹 给了我好多近距离的极佳活动
but I must admit you do have to feel sorry for the penguin,
但是我必须承认你得同情那只企鹅
just doesn't stand a chance.
实在是倒霉
The team knew where to find leopard seals,
摄制组知道找到豹斑海豹的地方
but finding the other top predator
然而发现其它顶级食肉动物
was going to be another matter entirely.
完全是另一码事情
Very little is known about Antarctic killer whales.
对于南极虎鲸了解甚少
Time to bring in reinforcements.
只得召唤援兵了
HMS Endurance,
坚韧号
the Royal Navy's ice patrol ship.
皇家海军冰上巡逻舰
She surveys Antarctic waters and the crew see changes every year.
她勘察南极水域 观察每年的变化
The latest chart of this area, we are now six miles inside an ice shelf, which just goes to show
这个区域的最新海图 我们现在深入冰架6英里
how much retreation of this ice shelf has occurred over the past five or six years.
这证明了这里的冰架在过去五 六年里已经退缩了多少
Would you get complications...?
你的难题是...
Series producer Martha Holmes and cameraman David Baillie
剧集制作人玛莎.霍姆斯和摄影师大卫.贝利
were on board to find and film the killer whales from the air.
登机希望在空中发现并拍摄到虎鲸
Endurance carries two Lynx helicopters used to assist
坚韧号携带有两架山猫直升机
the British Antarctic Survey and the Hydrographic Office.
用来帮助英国南极勘察及水文调查局
On this trip,
在这次旅行中
some time on one of the helicopters is assigned to the Life team.
有时一架直升机就交给了生活摄制组了
No-one has succeeded in filming killer whales hunting off the Antarctic peninsular before.
之前没人在南极半岛拍摄到虎鲸捕食
Our two teams have just a few days when they can film together.
我们两个摄制组在一起拍摄就只有几天时间
At water level the Golden Fleece has exciting news.
在金羊毛号的水面传来了激动的消息
They've found killer whales which look as though they could be hunting.
他们发现了虎鲸 样子好像是在捕食
And Navy 435, Navy 435, this is Golden Fleece, Golden Fleece over.
海军435 海军435 这里是金羊毛 金羊毛 结束
INDISTINCT VOICE ON RADIO
（电台里的模糊声）
'Copy that. We're on our way.'
再说一遍 我们在接近中
Guys, really windy, we'll be...
伙计 风好大 我们...
pretty lucky to stay with them through this. But we can try though.
真幸运与它们一路同行 尽管我们很费劲
435, this is Golden Fleece, we have lost sight of the orca.
435 这里是金羊毛 我们已经看不到虎鲸了
The white.'Yeah, OK, they're in direct line with that iceberg now,
白颜色的 对 它们现在与冰山在一条直线上
'between us and the iceberg about 100 metres this side of it.'
在我们与冰山之间 我们这一侧约100米处
'Visual. Yeah, visual.'
看见了 看见了
From the air, the helicopter team can follow the killer whales more easily than the boat team.
从空中 直升机摄制组跟踪虎鲸比船上那组要容易得多
435, this is Golden Fleece, full copy. Out.
435 这里是金羊毛 请重复 结束
By working together the helicopter and yacht are able to keep track of the whales in the rough sea.
依靠直升机和快艇的共同努力 能够在波涛汹涌中保持对虎鲸的跟踪
'There's four now actually yes, four, and four I can see.'
有四只 对 四只 我看到了四只
A change in the weather gives a chance to film at last.
天气终于给了拍摄一次机会
They've gone further up this way, if we follow them that's good.
它们已经走到前头了 如果我们没跟丢的话
But will they hunt?
然而它们会捕食吗？
OK, here they come through.
不错 它们过来了
Oops, yeah, they 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, it's a good 12 huh, easy.
噢耶 它们 1，2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,居然有12只
Doug has spotted a crabeater seal near some ice, buthave the killer whales seen it?
道格已经认出碎冰附近有只食虾海豹，然而虎鲸有没有看到它呢？
No, just keep loosening the square screen.
不 保持镜头
They have.
它们发现了
Some good action.
不错的动作
Can you go closer?
你还能更近些吗？
It's over, that's it, they've got him.
没戏了，它们已经抓住它了
It's still there.
还在那里
For a wildlife cameraman there are always surprises.
对于野生动物摄影师来说 总是惊喜不断
It has taken two months, but they've succeeded thanks to extraordinary
花了两个月 然而他们的成功多亏了
collaboration from an entire ship's company to a lone skipper.
从整个船公司到一个孤独的船长的通力合作
Collaborations like this would be the foundation of the whole three years of filming across the world.
这样的合作将是整整三年间世界各地拍摄的基础